-- shortest paths.
-- 最短路径
This is the finale.
这次是最终回了
Hopefully it was worth waiting for.
希望这次也是值得期待啊
Remind you there's a quiz coming up soon,
提醒一下 接下来会有个小测验哦亲
you should be studying for it.
是时候开始复习了
There's no problem set due at the same time
因为测验 我就不布置作业了
as the quiz because you should be studying now.
考虑到你们现在肯定要复习的
It's a take-home exam.
这是个课后测验
It's required that you come to class on Monday.
你们周一都必须回来上课
Of course, you'll all come, but everyone watching at home
当然 在座的都会来 不过现在在家看视频的人
should also come next Monday to get the quiz.
下周一也得回来参加考试
It's the required lecture.
这是课程的要求
So, we need a bit of a recap in the trilogy so far.
因此 我们要回顾下 到目前为止 这三部曲的重点
So, the last two lectures, first two episodes,
那么 上两次课 之前那两集
were about single source shortest paths.
是关于单源最短路径
So, we wanted to find the shortest path
那么 如果我们要找到最短路径
from a source vertex to every other vertex.
从源点到其他每个顶点的最短路径
And, we saw a few algorithms for this.
我们有这样几个算法来求解
Here's some recap. We saw in the unweighted case,
回顾一下 我们知道在未加权的情况下
that was sort of the easiest where all the edge weights were one.
这是最简单的 所有的边的长度都是1
Then we could use breadth first search.
那我们可以使用广度优先搜索算法
And this costs what we call linear time in the graph world,
它的时间复杂度 在图的范畴里是线性的
the number of vertices plus the number of edges.
即顶点数和边的数目之和
The next simplest case, perhaps,
而第二个最简单的情况
is nonnegative edge weights.
是非负权边
And in that case, what algorithm do we use?
在这个案例中 我们应该使用哪种算法呢
Dijkstra, all right, everyone's awake.
Dijkstra算法 挺带感嘛 大家都目光炯炯啊
Several answers at once, great.
都学会抢答了 果然是期末的节奏
So this takes almost linear time
所以这个基本上是线性时间
if you use a good heap structure,
如果你用对了堆结构的话
so, V log V plus E.
那就是V log V + E
And, in the general case, general weights,
而在一般情况下 对于一般的权值
we would use Bellman-Ford which you saw.
我们用的是Bellman-Ford算法
And that costs VE, good, OK, which is quite a bit worse.
这需要花费VE 矮油不错嘛 不过这个就略显低端了
This is ignoring log factors.
因为这个log可以忽略
Dijkstra is basically linear time,
所以 Dijkstra算法基本也是线性的
Bellman-Ford at least quadratic
但Bellman-Ford算法至少是平方阶的
if you have a connected graph.
如果你有一个连通图
So, in the sparse case, when E is order V,
所以在稀疏情况下 当E是V阶的时候
this is about linear. This is about quadratic.
这个是线性的 这个却是平方阶的
In the dense case, when E is about V^2,
在密集情况下 当E大约是V的平方的时候
this is quadratic, and this is cubic.
这个是平方阶的 而这个是立方阶的
So, Dijkstra and Bellman-Ford
所以 Dijkstra算法和Bellman-Ford算法
are separated by about an order of V factor,
是以一个V阶因数区分开的
which is pretty bad.
这就非常糟糕了
OK, but that's the best we know how to do
好的 但这是我们能想到的最好办法了
for single source shortest paths, negative edge weights,
对于单源最短路径 有负权边的情况下
Bellman-Ford is the best.
Bellman-Ford算法是最好的了
We also saw in recitation the case of a DAG.
我们在复习课中还看到DAG的情况
And there, what do you do?
这个怎么办？
[Student]Inaudible.
[学生]:……
[Prof]:Topological sort, yeah.
[教授]:拓扑排序 噢耶
So, you can do a topological sort
没错 你们可以用拓扑排序
to get an ordering on the vertices.
来得到这些顶点的顺序
That you run Bellman-Ford, one round.
来运行一次Bellman-Ford算法
This is one way to think of what's going on.
这是一种思考方式
You run Bellman-Ford in the order
在运行Bellman-Ford算法时
given by the topological sort, which is once,
按照拓扑排序得到的顺序
and you get a linear time algorithm.
然后你得到了一个线性时间算法
So, DAG is another case where we know how to do.
那么 我们也知道DAG的解法
Even with weights, unweighted, we can also do linear time
即使是加权 或未加权的情况 都可以用线性时间来做
Most of the time, though, will be,
绝大多数的情况下是这样
so you should keep these in mind that in the quiz,
这个一定要记住 在测验里
when you get a shortest path problem,
如果遇到了一个最短路径问题
or what you end up determining
或者是你最终确定
is the shortest path problem, think about
这是一个最短路径问题 想想看
what's the best algorithm you can use in that case.
在这情况下哪个算法会最好
OK, so that's single source shortest paths.
好的 这就是单源最短路径问题
And so, in our evolution of the Death Star,
那么 在我们死星的发展史中
initially it was just nonnegative edge weights.
最初这只是非负权边
Then we got negative edge weights.
然后我们遇到了负权边
Today, the Death Star challenges us
今天 死星又开了新的副本
with all pair shortest paths,
最终boss叫“全对最短路径”问题
where we want to know the shortest path weight
这次我们要求的
between every pair of vertices.
是每一对顶点之间的最短路径
OK, so let's get some quick results.
好 让我们看些显而易见的结果
What could we do with this case?
在这种情况下 我们怎么做？
So, for example, suppose I have an unweighted graph.
举个栗子 假设我有一个未加权的图
Any suggestions of how I should
大家有什么建议么
compute all pair shortest paths?
我该如何求出“全对最短路径”
Between every pair of vertices,
我想知道每一对顶点间
I want to know the shortest path weight.
它们的最短路径权重
[Student]:BFS.
[学生]：BFS（广度优先搜索）
[Prof]:BFS, a couple more words? Yeah?
[教授]：BFS 能多说点么亲？
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：……
[Prof]:Right, BFS V times. OK, I'll say V times BFS,
[教授]:好吧 用BFS搜索V次  我是说用V次BFS
OK? So, the running time would be V^2 plus V times E,
明白吧？ 所以我们的运行时间会是V^2 + V*E
yeah, which is assuming your graph is connected,
嗯 假设你的图是连通图
V times E.
那就是V乘以E
OK, good. That's probably about the best algorithm
好 很好 这大概是我们知道的最好的算法了
we know for unweighted graphs.
对于未加权图来说
So, a lot of these are going to sort of be the obvious answer.
所以 一切的一切都指向一个明显的答案
You take your single source algorithm, you run it V times.
你编写一个单源算法 然后运行它V次
That's the best you can do,
那就是最好的方法了
OK, or the best we know how to do.
或者是我们知道的最好方法了
This is not so bad.
这还挺不错嘛
This is like one iteration of Bellman-Ford for comparison
对比来看 这就像Bellman-Ford算法中的一次迭代
We definitely need at least,
我们肯定至少需要
like, V^2 time, because the size of the output is V^2,
大概V^2的时间 因为输出的大小是V^2
V^2 shortest path weight we have to compute.
我们必须计算V^2个最短路径权值
So, this is not perfect, but pretty good.
这并不是最完美的 不过还不赖
And we are not going to improve on that.
我们也不打算改进这方法了
So, nonnegative edge weights: the natural thing to do is
所以对于非负权边 最自然的解决方法就是
to run Dijkstra V times, OK, no big surprise.
运行Dijkstra算法V次 没啥好说的
And the running time of that is, well, V times E again,
所需要的运行时间是 嗯 还是V乘以E
plus V^2, log V, which is also not too bad.
加上V的平方 乘以log V  这个也不差
I mean, it's basically the same as running BFS.
我的意思是 这基本和BFS差不多
And then, there's the log factor.
然后 这还有个log因子
If you ignore the log factor, this is the dominant term.
如果你把log忽略不计 这个就是决定项了
And, I mean, this had an V^2 as well.
然后 这还有一个V的平方
So, these are both pretty good.
所以它们都挺不错的
I mean, this is kind of neat. Essentially,
我的意思是 这挺整洁的 但其实
the time it takes to run one Bellman-Ford plus a log factor
在运行Bellman-Ford再加一个log的因子的时间里
you can compute all pair shortest paths
你已经能够求出所有最短路径了
if you have nonnegative edge weights.
如果都是非负权边的话
So, I mean, comparing all pairs to signal source,
所以 我的意思是 比较单源和全对最短路径
this seems a lot better,
这个看起来就犀利多了
except we can only handle nonnegative edge weights.
当然我们只能处理非负权边
OK, so now let's think about the general case.
好 我们现在来设想更平凡的情况
Well, this is the focus of today,
嗯 这就是我们今天这课的重点
and here's where we can actually make an improvement.
也是我们可以作出改进的地方
So the obvious thing is V times Bellman-Ford,
显然 V次的Bellman-Ford算法
which would cost V^2 times E.
需要花费V^2*E
And that's pretty pitiful,
这就显得太渣了点
and we're going to try to improve that
我们现在就要调教它
to something closer to that nonnegative edge weight bound.
让它更接近这个非负权边的界
So it turns out, here, we can actually make an improvement
而结果是 我们确实可以做出相应的改进
whereas in these special cases,
而在这些特殊的情况中
we really can't do much better.
我们真心抢救不能
OK, I don't have a good intuition why,
好吧 我也说不出为什么
but it's the case.
但事实就是如此
So, we'll cover something like
我们将会涉及到
three algorithms today for this problem.
应对此问题的三个算法
The last one will be the best,
最后一个会是最好的
but along the way we'll see some nice connections
不过在过程中我们会看到一些
between shortest paths and dynamic programming,
最短路径与动态规划之间神奇的联系
which we haven't really seen yet.
这些是我们以前没有见过的
We've seen shortest path and applying greedy algorithms to it
我们看过了应用贪心算法来求最短路径
but today will actually do dynamic programming.
但今天我们做动态规划
The intuition is that with all pair shortest paths,
直观地说 对于“全对最短路径”
there's more potential subproblem reuse.
其实有很多潜在的可重用的子问题
We've got to compute the shortest path
我们要计算所有的x和y间
from x to y for all x and y.
从x到y的最短路径
Maybe we can reuse thoseshortest paths
或许 在计算其他最短路径时
in computing other shortest paths.
我们可以重用已经算好的路径
OK, there's a bit more reusability, let's say.
我们可以说 这就有了更多的可重用性了
OK, let me quickly define all pair shortest paths formally,
好 让我们快速定义一下 “全对最短路径”
because we're going to change our notation slightly.
因为接下来 我们要稍微改变一下表示法
It's because we care about all pairs.
这是因为我们现在关注的是“全对的”
So, as usual, the input is directed graph,
所以 好像以往一样 输入的是有向图
so, vertices and edges.
顶点和边
We're going to say that the vertices
我们说把这些顶点
are labeled one to n for convenience
为了方便 标记为从1到n
because we're going to think of things more, with all pairs,
因为对于“全对的”来说
we're going to think of things more as an n by n matrix
我们最好是把它想象成一个n阶矩阵
instead of edges in some sense
来替代通常意义的边
because it doesn't help to think
因为如果用邻接表的话
any more in terms of adjacency lists.
不是那么容易理解
And, you have edge weights as usual.
按惯例 这些边也是加权的
This is what makes it interesting.
这就是有趣的地方
Some of them are going to be negative.
有些边会变成负的
So, w maps to every real number,
w 可以是全体实数
and the target output is a shortest path matrix.
而输出目标就是最短路径矩阵
So, this is now an n by n matrix.
所以这现在是一个n阶矩阵
So, n is just the number of vertices
n只是顶点的数目
of shortest path weights.
表示最短路径权重的矩阵
So, delta of I, j is the shortest path weight from i to j
那么δ(i,j)是从i到j的最短路径权重
for all pairs of vertices.
对于所有的顶点对
So this, you could represent
所以 你可以把这个表示为
as an n by n matrix in particular.
一个n阶矩阵
OK, so now let's start doing algorithms.
好 现在开始我们的算法
So, we have this very simple algorithm,
首先我们有非常简单的算法
V times Bellman-Ford,
V次的Bellman-Ford算法
V^2 times E, and just for comparison's sake,
E*V^2 为了比较
I'm going to say, let me rewrite that,
我要说 让我们重新写下这些
V times Bellman-Ford gives us this running time of V^2 E,
V次的Bellman-Ford算法耗费E*V^2运行时间
and I'm going to think about the case where,
我将会考虑这个情况
let's just say the graph is dense,
我们就说这个图是稠密的吧
meaning that the number of edges is quadratic,
就是说遇到的边缘数是平方的
in the number of vertices.
是顶点数的平方阶
So in that case, this will take V^4 time,
在这个情况下 我们会花费V^4的时间
which is pretty slow. We'd like to do better.
这样就非常慢了 我们可以做得更好些
So, first goal would just be to beat V^4, V hypercubed,
所以 第一目标是解决V^4  V的超立方
I guess. OK, and we are going to
但愿如此 好吧 我们应该
use dynamic programming to do that.
用动态规划搞定它
Or at least that's what the motivation will come from.
或者至少这该是我们的动力所在
It will take us a while before we can even beat V^4,
解决V^4的路漫漫其修远兮
which is maybe a bit pathetic,
可能还会有些乏味
but it takes some clever insights, let's say.
但这需要睿智的洞察力
OK, so I'm going to introduce
好 下面我会介绍
a bit more notation for this graph.
这个图的一些表示法
So, I'm going to think about
我也将会考虑
the weighted adjacency matrix.
加权邻接矩阵
So, I don't think we've really seen this in lecture before,
在以前的课没讲过这个
although I think it's in the appendix.
虽然附录里有
What that means,
这就意味着
so normally adjacency matrix is like
通常 邻接矩阵都会是
one if there's an edge, and zero if there isn't.
有边相邻记1 否则记0
And this is in a digraph,
这是在有向图中
so you have to be a little bit careful.
所以你们得小心一点
Here, these values, the entries in the matrix,
而在此 这些矩阵里的元素
are going to be the weights of the edges.
都会是边的权值
OK, this is if ij is an edge.
好 这里如果ij是一条边
So, if ij is an edge in the graph,
所以 如果ij是图里的一条边
and it's going to be infinity if there is no edge.
如果没有边的话则是正无穷
OK, in terms of shortest paths,
好 用最短路径来表示
this is a more useful way to represent the graph.
这是个更好用的表述图的方法
All right, and so this includes everything
好 这就包涵了我们这里
that we need from here.
所需要的东西了
And now we just have to think about it as a matrix.
现在我们需要把它当成矩阵来考虑
Matrices will be a useful tool in a little while.
接下来 矩阵会成为一个很有用的工具
OK, so now I'm going to define some sub problems.
好 我现在要定义一些子问题了
And, there's different ways that you could define
你们可以用不同的方法来定义
what's going on in the shortest paths problem.
最短路径问题里的具体情况
The natural thing is I want to go from vertex i to vertex j
但自然地  我会想 从顶点I到顶点J
What's the shortest path?
最短路径是什么
OK, we need to refine the sub problems
好 我们需要更深入地
a little bit more than that. Not surprising.
细化子问题  就是这样
And if you think about my analogy to Bellman-Ford,
好好回想下吧 我是怎么类推Bellman-Ford的
what Bellman-Ford does is it tries to
Bellman-Ford的做法是
build longer and longer shortest paths.
构建越来越长的最短路径
But here, length is in terms of the number of edges.
但在这里 长度是依据边的数目而定
So, first, it builds shortest paths of length one.
首先 它构建了长度为一的最短路径
We've proven the first round it does that.
我们证明了在第一轮它是这样的
The second round,
在第二轮里
it provides all shortest paths of length two,
它给出了所有的长度为二的最短路径
of... count two, and so on.
呃...边的数目为二  如此类推
We'd like to do that sort of analogously,
我们喜欢类推
and try to reuse things a little bit more.
然后重用之前的计算结果
So, I'm going to say d sub ij superscript m
那么 我定义d  下标ij  上标m
is the weight of the shortest path from i to j
它是从i到j的最短路径的权值
with some restriction involving m.
并有一个限制条件m
So shortest path from i to j using at most m edges.
那么这是从i到j的最短路径  最多用m条边
OK, for example, if m is zero,
举个例子 如果m是零的话
then we don't have to really think very hard
那样我们就不用想破头地
to find all shortest paths of length zero.
去找出长度为零的最短路径了
OK, they use zero edges, I should say.
我应该说 是用了零条边的最短路径
So, Bellman-Ford sort of tells us
而Bellman-Ford算法则提示我们
how to go from m to m plus one.
如何从m前进到m+1
So, let's just figure that out.
那我们就来想想看吧
So one thing we know from the Bellman-Ford analysis
我们从Bellman-Ford算法中分析知道的一件事
is if we look at d ij superscript m-1,
就是如果我们观察 d_ij 上标m-1
we know that in some sense
我们知道 在某种意义上
the longest shortest path of relevance,
最长的对应最短路径
unless you have negative weight cycle,
除非出现了负权环
is when m equals n minus one
出现在m=n-1时
because that's the longest simple path you can have.
因为那是你能找到的最长的简单路径了
So, this should be a shortest path weight from i to j,
所以这应该就是从i到j的最短路径值了
and it would be no matter
这与你的上标
what larger value you put in the superscript.
输入的是多大的值没有任何关系
This should be delta of i comma j
这应该是δ(i,j)
if there's no negative weight cycles.
如果没有负权环
OK, so this feels good for dynamic programming.
好 这动态规划还挺不错的
This will give us the answer
这就给出了答案
if we can compute this for all m.
只要我们能算出所有m的对应值
Then we'll have the shortest path weights in particular.
那我们就可以得到具体的最短路径权值
We need a way to detect negative weight cycles,
我们需要一个方法来发现负权环
but let's not worry about that too much for now.
但我们现在还不需要着急这些
There are negative weights, but let's just assume for now
虽然有负权数 但我们先假设
there's no negative weight cycles.
这里没有负权环
OK, and we get a recursion recurrence.
好 那我们就得到了一个循环递归
And the base case is when m equals zero.
初始情况是当m等于零的时候
This is pretty easy.
这个很简单了
They have the same vertices the weight of zero
顶点相同 则权值为零
and otherwise it's infinity.
否则就是正无穷
OK, and then the actual recursion is for m.
好 接下来是m的实际递归情况
OK, if I got this right, this is a pretty
如果我没手滑 这个就是很
intuitive recursion for d_ij of m is
直观的递归  因为d_ij 上标m是
a min of smaller things in terms of m minus one.
用m-1项求得的最小值
I'll just draw a picture,
我画个图来解释
and then the proof of that claim should be obvious.
这样一来 这个证明就很显然了
So, this is proof by picture. So, we have on the one hand,
这个是画图证明   所以一方面说
i over here, and j over here.
i在这儿 j在这儿
We want to know the shortest path from i to j.
我们想知道从i到j的最短路径
And, we want to use, at most, m edges.
接下来我们要用至多m条边
So, the idea is, well,
所以思路是 嗯
you could use m minus one edges to get somewhere.
你可以用m-1条边先到一些地方
So this is, at most,
所以这是 最多
m minus one edges, some other place,
用m-1条边 到其他地方
and we'll call it k. So this is a candidate for k.
我们就叫它k吧  这是其中的一个k
And then you could take the edge directly from k to j.
然后你可以直接获得从k到j的边长
So, this costs a_kj, and this costs d_ik, m minus one.
所以这花费a_kj 这需要d_ik 上标m-1
OK, and that's a candidate path of length that uses,
好 这是其中一个候选路径
at most, m edges from i to j.
最多用m条边从i到j
And this is essentially just considering all of them.
这实际上已经考虑到全部情况了
OK, so there's sort of many paths we are considering.
好 那就有蛮多路径需要考虑的了
All of these are candidate values of k.
那么这些都是k的候选项
We are taking them in over all k
我们都用k来表示
as intermediate nodes, whatever.
作为过渡点  随便啦
So there they are. We take the best such path.
就是这样  我们选择这些最好的路径
That should encompass all shortest paths.
这就包含了所有的最短路径
And this is essentially sort of
这本质上就是
what Bellman-Ford is doing,
Bellman-Ford算法做的事儿
although not exactly. We also sort of want to think about,
虽然不完全是 但我们还会这样想
What if I just go directly with, say, m minus one edges?
如果我直接说 就只有m-1条边呢？
What if there is no edge here that I want to use？
如果这里根本没有我用的上的边呢？
in some sense?
在某种意义上？
Well, we always think about there being,
嗯 我们总是认为
and the way the A's are defined,
这些a都已经定义好了
there's always this zero weight edge to yourself.
而且总有零权边  就是从自己到自己
So, you could just take a path that's shorter,
所以 你们可以用一个更加短的路径
go from d i to j, and j is a particular value of k
从i到j  而j则是k的一个特殊值
that we might consider, and then
我们可以这样想  然后
take a zero weight edge at the end from a_jj.
最后用一个零权的边  a_jj
OK, so this really encompasses everything.
好 这就涵盖一切方案了
So that's a pretty trivial claim.
所以这个没什么大不了的
Clear? now once we have such a recursion,
懂没？ 现在我们建立了这个递归式
we get a dynamic program.
我们就有了动态规划
I mean, there, this is it in some sense.
我的意思是 在某种意义上是的
It's written recursively. You can write a bottom up.
这是个递归的语句 你可以写成自底向上法
And I would like to write it bottom up a little bit
我是有点喜欢自底向上法
because, well it doesn't look like it,
因为 这样写不像是它的风格
this is a relaxation.
这是一种松弛操作
This is yet another relaxation algorithm.
这是另一种松弛算法
So, I'll give you, so this is sort of the algorithm.
我会给出 嗯 这就是这种算法
This is not a very interesting algorithm.
这不是一种很有趣的算法
So, you don't have to write it all down
所以你们不需要把这它都写下来
if you don't feel like it.
如果你们不喜欢它
It's probably not even in the book.
它很有可能也不在书里
This is just an intermediate step.
这只是一个中间步骤
So, we loop over all m.
我们循环所有的m值
That's sort of the outermost thing to do.
这差不多是最基本的事了
I want to build longer and longer paths,
我想要构建一个越来越长的路径
and this vaguely corresponds to Bellman-Ford,
这模糊地对应了Bellman-Ford算法
although it's actually worse than Bellman-Ford.
虽然它实际上要比Bellman-Ford算法糟糕
But hey, what the heck?
诶我
It's a stepping stone. OK, then for all i and j,
这是块垫脚石 好 然后对于所有的i和j
and then we want to compute this min.
接下来 我们要计算这个最小值
So, we'll just loop over all k, and relax.
我们把所有k值过一遍 然后进行松弛
And, here's where we're actually computing the min.
这儿就是我们要计算最小值的地方
And, it's a relaxation, is the point.
这个是松弛操作  这个是重点
This is our good friend, the relaxation step,
松弛法是我们的好伙伴
relaxing edge. Well, it's not,
松弛边 好吧 这不是
yeah. I guess we're relaxing edge kj, or something,
唷 我想我们要松弛kj边 或者别的什么
except we don't have the same clear notion.
只是我们不再有一个清晰的表达方式
I mean, it's a particular thing that we're relaxing.
我的意思是 我们松弛的是个特别的东西
It's not just a single edge
并不只是一条单独的边
because we don't have a single source anymore.
因为这不再是单源了
It's now relative to source i,
现在是相对于源i来说
we are relaxing the edge kj,
我们在松弛kj这条边
something like that. But this is clearly a relaxation.
差不多吧  但这的确是松弛法
We are just making the triangle inequality true
我们现在就是在使三角不等式成立
if it wasn't before.
如果以前不成立的话
The triangle inequality has got to hold between all pairs.
三角不等式应该在所有点对之间都成立
And that's just implementing this min, right?
同时 这也是在实现这个取最小值吧？
You're taking d_ij.
你在用d_ij.
You take the min of what it was before in some sense.
在某种意义上  你是给之前的结果取最小值
That was one of the possibilities we considered
这是我们考虑的一种可能方案
when we looked at the zero weight edge.
如果我们研究零权边的话
We say, well, or you could go from i to some k
或者说 你先从i到某一个k
in some way that we knew how to before,
用上一些我们已知的结果
and then add on the edge,
然后再加上这条边
and check whether that's better if it's better,
然后看看跟原来相比会不会更好
set our current estimate to that.
如果会 则赋予现有的估值
And, you do this for all k. In particular,
你可以对所有的k这样做 尤其是
you might actually compute something smaller than this min
你确实有可能算出 比这个最小值还要小的值
because I didn't put superscripts up here.
因为我这里没有写上标
But that's just making paths even better.
但是那样只会让路径更好
OK, so you have to argue that
好了 你们现在可以说
relaxation is always a good thing to do.
松弛一直是个不错的选择
So, by not putting superscripts,
那么  不加上标
maybe I do some more relaxation,
可能我可以做更多的松弛
but more relaxation never hurts us.
毕竟  更多的松弛也没有什么坏处
You can still argue correctness using this claim.
你仍然可以用这个证明来验证正确性
So, it's not quite the direct implementation,
这不是很直接的实现方法
but there you go, dynamic programming algorithm.
但是动态规划就是这样
The main reason I'll write it down
我要写下它的主要理由是
so you see that it's a relaxation,
你也知道  这是个松弛操作
and you see the running time is n^4,
而它的运算时间为 n^4
OK, which is certainly no better than Bellman-Ford.
好吧 它肯定没有Bellman-Ford好
Bellman-Ford was n^4 even in the dense case,
即使在密集的情况下  Bellman-Ford 也是n^4
and it's a little better in the sparse case.
在稀疏情况下会稍好一点
So not doing so great.
所以这个并不是很好
But it's a start.
不过这是个开始
OK, it gets our dynamic programming minds thinking.
它只是让我们着眼于动态规划
And, we'll get a better dynamic program in a moment.
很快我们就会想到更好地动态规划了
But first,
但首先
there's actually something useful we can do with this formulation,
实际上 这条等式还是能派上用场的
and I guess I'll ask,
我会先问问你们
but I'll be really impressed if anyone can see.
先想到的人能提升好感度哦
Does this formula look like anything else
这个等式让你联想到什么？
that you've seen in any context,
你曾经在哪里看到过的？
mathematical or algorithmic?
数学模型或者算法？
Have you seen that recurrence anywhere else?
你是否在什么地方看到过这个循环体？
OK, not exactly as stated, but similar.
好吧  当然不是一模一样  但是差不多
I'm sure if you thought about it for a while,
我相信如果你们思考一会
you could come up with it. Any answers?
是可以想出来的  有答案了吗
I didn't think you would be very intuitive,
意识啊 骚年
but the answer is matrix multiplication.
这个答案是矩阵乘法
And it may now be obvious to you, or it may not.
现在这对你们来讲应该很明显了  也可能不是
You have to think with the right quirky mind.
如果你有很准确而独到的洞察力
Then it's obvious that it's matrix multiplication.
你就会发现它明显就是矩阵乘法
Remember, matrix multiplication,
记住  矩阵乘法
we have A, B, and C.
我们有A,B,C
They're all n by n matrices.
它们都是n阶矩阵
And, we want to compute C equals A times B.
我们想计算出C=A*B
And what that meant was, well,
那它就意味着  呃
c_ij was a sum over all k of a_ik times b_kj.
c_ij= ∑(a_ik * b_kj)  对于所有k
All right, that was our definition of matrix multiplication
好了  这就是对矩阵乘法的定义
And that formula looks kind of like this one.
那个公式看起来就跟这个一样
I mean, notice the subscripts: ik and kj.
我的意思是  注意这些下标  ik和kj
Now, the operators are a little different.
现在  这个运算有点不同
Here, we're multiplying the inside things
在这里 我们是把里面的东西相乘
and adding them all together.
然后把它们全部相加
There, we're adding the inside things and taking them in.
而在那边 我们把里面的加起来 并且放进来
But other than that, it's the same.
但除此之外 它们都是相同的
OK, weird, but here we go.
好吧 很神奇 但就是这样
So, the connection to shortest paths
那么 要想跟最短路径扯上关系
is you replace these operators.
你先要替换掉这些运算
So, let's take matrix multiplication and replace,
让我们来改造矩阵乘法吧
what should I do first, plus this thing with min.
先要干嘛  用求最小值 替换这个求和
So, why not,  just change the operators,
我们仅仅是改变运算方法
replace dot with plus?
把点乘替换成加法
This is just a different algebra to work in,
这只是换了一套不同的代数来做
where plus actually means min,
这里的加号实际上是求最小值
and dot actually means plus.
点乘号实际上是加号
So, you have to check that things sort of work out in that context,
因此 你必须去检验一下 是不是真的能这么用
but if we do that, then we get that c_ij
但如果可以的话  我们就会得到 c_ij
is the min overall k of a_ik plus b_kj
等于 对于所有k   a_ik加上b_kj 的最小值
And that looks like what we actually want to compute,
这应该就是我们实际要算的东西
here, for one value of m,
这里  因为有一个m值
you have to sort of do this m times.
所以 你必须迭代m次
But this conceptually is d_ij^m, and this is d_ik^(m-1).
而这个其实就是d_ij上标m  这个是d_ik上标m-1
So, this is looking like a matrix product,
因此 这看起来像是一个矩阵乘积
which is kind of cool.
酷炫啊
So, if we sort of plug in this claim,
因此  如果我们带入上面那个定义
then, and think about things as matrices,
然后在联系一下矩阵运算
The cliam, the recurrence gives us,
这个定义 这个循环就给出了...
and I'll just write this now at matrix form,
现在我用矩阵的形式来表示
that d^m, is d^(m-1), funny product, A.
D上标m等于 D上标m-1  圈圈乘一个A
All right, so these are the weights.
好了 这些就是权值
These were the weighted adjacency matrix.
这些是带权值的邻接矩阵
This was the previous d value.
这是前面那个D的值
This is the new d value.
这个是新的D的值
So, I'll just rewrite that
我就把它们重新写成
in matrix form with capital letters.
用矩阵的形式  用大写字母来表示
OK, I have the circle up things
好的 我这个圈圈乘
that are using this funny algebra,
就代表了刚才说的这种代数运算
so, in particular, circled product.
所以 这是一个特殊的圈乘
OK, so that's kind of nifty.
好的  有点小技巧
We know something about computing matrix multiplications.
我们对矩阵乘法的计算有了一些了解
We can do it in n^3 time.
我们可以在n^3 的时间内完成
If we were a bit fancier,
如果我们爆发小宇宙的话
maybe we could do it in sub-cubic time.
可能还可以在次立方的时间内完成
So, we could try to sort of use this connection.
所以 我们可以尽量利用这种联系
And, well, think about what we are computing here.
好好回想下吧 我们这儿算的是到底是什么
We are saying, well,
我们说的是
d to the m is the previous one times A.
D上标m等于 它的前一项圈乘A
So, what is d^m?
这个D上标m是什么？
Is that some other algebraic notion that we know?
是不是我们知道的某个代数概念？
[student]Inaudible
[学生]:...
[Prof]:Yeah, it's the exponent.
[教授]:没错 就是指数
We're taking A, and we want to raise it to the power, m,
我们用一个A  希望把这个D的上标提升为m
with this funny notion of product.
用这个圈圈乘的概念
So, in other words,
换句话讲
d to the m is really just A to the m in a funny way.
D上标m  你可以把它看成是A的圈圈上标m
So, I'll circle it,
因此  我将把它圈出来
OK? So, that sounds good.
好吧？ 听起来不错
We also know how to compute powers of things relatively quickly,
我们也知道如何更快地求幂
if you remember how. OK, I need to define for this notion,
如果你记得怎么样做的话  我要定义这个概念
this power notion, to make sense,
这个幂的概念  要理解它
I should say what A to the zero means.
我应该说说A的零次方是什么意义
And so, I need some kind of identity matrix.
所以 我需要某种单位矩阵
And for here, the identity matrix is this one,
就目前而言  单位矩阵是这个
if I get it right.
如果我没搞错的话
So, it has zeros along the diagonal,
沿着对角线都是零
and infinities everywhere else.
其它都是正无穷
OK, that sort of just to match this definition.
这个仅仅是为了匹配这个定义
d_ij zero should be zeros on the diagonals
d_ij 上标0 应该就是对角线上的零
and infinity everywhere else.
然后其它都是正无穷
But you can check this is actually an identity.
但是你可以验证这其实是一个单位矩阵
If you multiply it with this
如果你用它乘以
funny multiplication against any other matrix,
用这个圈圈乘来跟其它矩阵相乘
you get the matrix back. Nothing changes.
你会得到原来的矩阵  什么都没变
This really is a valid identity matrix.
这真的是一个有效的单位矩阵
And, I should mention that for A to the m to make sense,
我应该提到对A的m次方的理解
you really knew that your product operation is associative
你们应该知道这个圈乘运算是有结合律的
So, actually A to the m circled makes sense
所以A的m圈次方成立
because circled multiplication is associative,
因为这个圈圈乘法符合结合律
and you can check that; not hard because,
你可以检验一下  不难的
I mean, min is associative, and addition is associative,
我的意思是说  min和加法都满足结合律
and all sorts of good stuff.
各种神奇
And, you have some kind of distributivity property.
而且它还符合分配律
And, this is, in turn,
这个是依次的
because the real numbers with,
因为实数和...
and get the right order here,
这个顺序要正确
with min as your addition operation,
用min替换加法运算
and plus as your multiplication operation
用加法替换乘法运算
is a closed semi-ring.
是一个闭合的半环
So, if ever you want to know
如果你想知道
when powers make sense, this is a good rule.
当指数有意义时  这就是个不错的规则
If you have a closed semi-ring,
如果你有一个闭合的半环
then matrix products on that semi-ring
那么半环上进行矩阵积
will give you an associative operator,
就会是符合结合律的运算
and then, good, you can take products.
那么  很好  你可以尽情地乘了
OK, that's just some formalism.
好了 那只是一些形式化的东西
So now, we have some intuition.
现在 我们有了一些直观的东西
The question is, what's the right algorithm?
问题在于 什么是正确的算法？
There are many possible answers,
这有很多可能的回答
some of which are right, some of which are not.
有些是对的  有些则不然
So, we have this connection to matrix products,
那么  总之我们跟矩阵乘法扯上了关系
and we have a connection to matrix powers.
跟矩阵指数也扯上了关系
And, we have algorithms for both.
对于两个 我们都有对应的算法
The question is, what should we do?
问题来了  我们应该怎么做？
So, all we need to do now is
我们现在所需要做的就是
to compute A to the funny power, n minus one.
计算A的n-1次方  那个圈次方
n minus one is when we get shortest paths,
n-1就是我们得到的最短路径
assuming we have no negative weight cycles.
假设我们没有负权环的话
In fact, we could compute a larger power than n minus one.
事实上  我们可以计算一个比n-1更大的次方
Once you get beyond n minus one,
一旦超过了n-1
multiplying by A doesn't change you anymore.
再乘以A也不会产生任何改变
So, how should we do it?
那我们应该怎么做
OK, you're not giving any smart answers.
好吧 你们都木有想法
I'll give the stupid answer.
让我来抛砖引玉一下吧
You could say, well, I take A.
你可以这么说  我先拿个A
I multiply it by A. Then I multiply it by A...
用A乘以它  再用A乘以它
and I use normal boring matrix to multiplication.
不断重复无聊的矩阵乘法
So, I do, like, n minus two,
我就这么做  一共做了N-2次
standard matrix multiplies. So, standard multiply costs,
标准的矩阵乘法  标准乘法复杂度是
like, n^3. And I'm doing n of them.
n^3  现在我要算n次
So, this gives me an n^4 algorithm,
所以这给我一个n^4的算法
and compute all the shortest pathways in n^4. Woohoo!
在n^4时间里算出所有的最短路径  喔呼
OK, no improvement. So, how can I do better?
好吧 还是那囧样   这到底要怎么破？
[student]Inaudible
[学生]:...
[Prof]:Right, natural thing to try which sadly does not work,
[教授]:对  最自然会想到的 虽然还是不起效
is to use the sub-cubic matrix multiply algorithm.
就是用次立方的矩阵乘积算法
We will, in some sense, get there in a moment
嗯 其实我们也快要讲到了
with a somewhat simpler problem.
跟一个更简单的问题一起讲
But, it's actually not known how to compute shortest paths
但实际上 我们不知道要怎么运用快速矩阵乘法
using fast matrix multiplication
来计算最短路径
like Strassen's system algorithm.
比如Strassen系统算法
But, good suggestion. OK, you have to think about
不过这是个好建议  好了  你们必须思考一下
why it doesn't work, and I'll tell you.
为什么它不起作用  这个我会告诉你
But it's not obvious,
但它不是很明显
so it's a perfectly reasonable suggestion.
这是个非常合理的建议
But in this context it doesn't quite work.
但是在这个情况下   它基本没用
It will come up in a few moments.
我们很快就会说到
The problem is,
这个问题是
Strassen requires the notion of subtraction.
Strassen 要求有减法的概念
And here, addition is min.
在这里 加法被换成了取最小值
And, there's no inverse to min.
而且 min是不可逆的
Once you take the arguments,
一旦你选择了某个参数
you can't sort of undo a min.
你不能随便撤销一个min
OK, so there's no notion of subtraction,
因此 没有减法这一概念
so it's not known how to pull that off, sadly.
更悲剧的是  我们不知道怎么消掉它
So, what other tricks do we have up our sleeve?Yeah?
那么  我们还有什么大招没放  嗯？
[student]Inaudible
[学生]:...
[Prof]:Divide and conquer, log n powering
[教授]:分治法 log n的乘方
yeah, repeated squaring.
对了 重复乘方的方法
That works. Good, we had a fancy way.
那样会有效  好极了  我们有了个很棒的方法
If you had a number n, you sort of looked at
如果你有一个数字n  你可以观察它
the binary number representation of n,
把n用二进制编码来表示
and you either squared the number
你可以把这个数写成平方的乘方形式
or squared it and added another factor of A.
或者平方后再乘上A的另一个因数
Here, we don't even have to be smart about it.
这里我们甚至可以脑残一点
OK, we can just compute,
我们只需要计算
we really only have to think about powers of two.
我们仅仅需要考虑2的幂
What we want to know,
我们想知道的是
and I'm going to need a bigger font here because there's
这里我现在需要把字写大一点
multiple levels of subscripts, A to the circled power,
因为会有好多层下标  A的圈次方
two to the ceiling of log n.
2的log n向上取整次方
Actually, n minus one would be enough.
事实上  n-1就足够了
But there you go. You can write n
不过就这样吧 你可以写n
if you didn't leave yourself enough space like me,
如果你跟我一样没地方写的话
n the ceiling, n the circle.
log n向上取整的圈次方
This just means the next power of two after n minus one,
这个意思是n-1的下一个2的幂
two to the ceiling log.
是2的┌log┐次方
So, we don't have to go directly to n minus one.
因此我们没必要直接去到n-1
We can go further because
我们可以更进一步  因为
anything farther than n minus one
任何比n-1更多的
is still just the shortest pathways.
都会是最短路径
If you look at the definition,
如果你再看看定义
and you know that your paths are simple,
你就知道你的路径是单一的
which is true if you have no negative weight cycles,
如果没有负权环的话就成立
then fine, just go farther.
那好吧  就走远一点吧
Why not? And so, to compute this,
为什么不呢  那么要计算这个
we just do ceiling of log n minus one products,
我们只要做┌log (n-1)┐次相乘
just take A squared,
我们只用算A的平方
and then take the result and square it
接着用这个结果进行平方 再平方...
So, this is order log n multiply some squares.
这就是O(log n)乘上平方运算的复杂度
And, we don't know how to use Strassen,
我们不知道怎么使用Strassen
but we can use the boring,
但是我们可以使用这个无聊的
standard multiply of n^3,
n^3的标准乘法
and that gives us n^3 log n running time,
得出O(n^3  log n)的运算时间
OK, which finally is something
好了 这个东西最终
that beats Bellman-Ford in the dense case.
会在密集情况下胜于Bellman-Ford
OK, in the dense case, Bellman-Ford was n^4.
在密集情况下  Bellman-Ford是O(n^4)
Here we get n^3 log n, finally something better.
这里得到的是O(n^3 log n)  终于逆转了
In the sparse case, it's about the same,
在稀疏情况下  两者差不多
maybe a little worse. E is order V.
可能差一点  E是V阶
Then we're going to get, like, V^3 for Bellman-Ford.
我们将得到  Bellman-Ford是O(V^3)
Here, we get n^3 log n. OK, after log factors,
这里我们有O(n^3 log n)   但毕竟这个log因子
this is an improvement some of the time.
也算是一个进步
OK, it's about the same the other times.
好吧  在其它时候差不多是一样的
Another nifty thing that you get for free out of this,
这个算法还自带一个被动技能
is you can detect negative weight cycles.
就是可以检测到负权环
So, here's a bit of a puzzle.
这里有点疑问
How would I detect, after I compute this product,
我算过了这个乘积后 还怎么检测负环？
A to the power to ceiling log n minus one,
A的2的[log(n-1)]次方
how would I know if I found a negative weight cycle?
我要怎么样知道自己发现了一个负权环
What would that mean in this matrix
在这矩阵里它是代表什么呢？
of all pairwise shortest path of at most a certain length?
这矩阵里的最短路径 都应该是某个有限长度的吧？
If I found a cycle,
如果我发现一个循环
what would have to be in that matrix? Yeah?
这矩阵肯定会变成怎样？   嗯？
[student]Inaudible
[学生]:...
[Prof]:Right, so I could, for example,
[教授]:对  我可以 比方说
take this thing, multiply it by A,
把这个东西 乘一个A
see if the matrix changed at all.
看看这矩阵有没有变化
Right, that works fine. That's what we do in Bellman-Ford
好吧  这的确可行  我们在Bellman-Ford中就是这么做的
It's an even simpler thing.
但这里甚至更简单
It's already there. You don't have to multiply.
它已经是那样了  你都不用做乘法了
But that's the same running time.
但是  这个运算时间是相同的
That's a good answer.
恭喜你 答对了
The diagonal would have a negative value, yeah.
对角线上会有一个负值 很好
So, this is just a cute thing. Both approaches would work,
因此  这是个很好玩的事情  两种方法都有效
can detect a negative weight cycle
都能检测一个负权环
just by looking at the diagonal of the matrix.
仅仅是通过监测矩阵的对角线
You just look for a negative value in the diagonal. OK.
你只要在这个对角线上找负值就好
So, that's algorithm one, let's say.
我们姑且称之为算法一
I mean, we've seen several that are all bad,
我是说  虽然我们说了很多无效的 方法
but I'll call this number one.
但是我将称这个为第一
OK, we'll see two more.
好  我们再多看两个
This is the only one that will,
这将是唯一的一个
well, I shouldn't say that.
喔唷  我不应该这么说
Fine, there we go.
随便吧  我们继续
So, this is one dynamic program that wasn't so helpful,
这是一个没多大帮助的动态规划
except it showed us a connection to matrix multiplication,
除了它给我们展示了一个与矩阵乘法的联系
which is interesting.
这点很有爱
We'll see why it's useful a little bit more.
你们会看到它还有什么用
But, it bled to this nasty four nested loops.
但它却带来了这个恶心的四层嵌套循环
And, using this trick, we got down to n^3 log n.
运用这个技巧  我们可以把复杂度降到O(n^3 log n)
Let's try, just for n^3.
让我们试一下  就用n^3
OK, just get rid of that log. It's annoying.
只要除去log就好  这东西很烦人
It makes you a little bit worse than Bellman-Ford,
这让你变得比 Bellman-Ford的还糟糕
in the sparse case.
在稀疏的情况下
So, let's just erase one of these nested loops.
让我们先擦掉这些嵌套循环中的一个
OK, I want to do that.
好的 我想这么做
OK, obviously that algorithm doesn't work
很显然这个算法就没用了
because at first there is a k, and it's not defined,
因为这本来有个k  现在却没有定义了
but, you know, I've got enough variables.
但是你看  我们已经有足够多的变量了
Why don't I just define k to be m?
我为什么不直接定义把k为m？
OK, it turns out that works.
实际上 这是可行的
I'll do it from scratch, but why not? Right?
我先从打草稿开始  不来一发吗？  是吧？
I don't know if that's how Floyd and Warshall
我不知道Floyd和Warshall
came up with their algorithm,
是不是就是这样想出这算法的
but here you go. Here's Floyd-Warshall.
但我们是这样  这就是Floyd-Warshall算法
The idea is to define
这个思路是
the subproblems a little bit more cleverly
用更聪明的方式来定义这些子问题
so that to compute one of these values,
所以要计算这其中的一个值
you don't have to take the min of n things.
你没必要去算n个东西的最小值
I just want to take the min of two things.
我只要2个中的最小就好
If I could do that, and I still only have n^3 subproblems,
如果我这么做  我仍然只有n^3子问题
then I would have n^3 time.
那么我还要n^3的时间
So, all right, the running time of dynamic program
因此  好吧  这个动态规划的运算时间
is number of subproblems times
就是子问题的数目乘上
the time to compute the recurrence for one subproblem.
计算一个子问题循环的时间
So, here's linear times n^3,
所以这是线性时间乘上n^3
and we want n^3 times constant. That would be good.
我们让n^3不变  但那样还不错
So that's Floyd-Warshall.
这就是 Floyd-Warshall算法
So, here's the way we're going to redefine c_ij.
现在我们即将重新定义c_ij
Or I guess, there it was called d_ij.
我觉得  也可以称之为 d_ij
Good, so we're going to define something new.
不错  我们要定义一些新的东西
So, d_ij superscript k is now going to be
d_ij上标k  现在要变成
the weight of the shortest path from i to j as before.
从i到j的最短路径的权重  跟以前一样
Notice I used the superscript k instead of m
注意我用这个上标k代替m
because I want k and m to be the same thing.
因为我想让k和m变成同一个东西
Deep. OK, now, here's the new constraint.
掂！ 现在 这里有个新的约束条件
I want all intermediate vertices along the path,
我想让这条路径上所有的媒介点
meaning all vertices except for i and j
也就是除了i和j的所有顶点
at the beginning and the end to have a small label.
从头到尾的所有点都有一个小标签
So, they should be in the set from one up to k.
它们应该属于一个从1到k的集合
And this is where we are really using that
这里实际上我们真正做的
our vertices are labeled one up to m.
是把顶点被标注为1到m
So, I'm going to say, well,
我会说 好吧
first think about the shortest paths
首先考虑这样一条最短路径
that don't use any other vertices.
它没用经过任何顶点
That's when k is zero.
这时k=0
Then think about all the
接着考虑一下所有的
shortest paths that maybe they use vertex one.
可能经过顶点一的最短路径
And then think about the shortest paths
然后再考虑那些
that maybe use vertex one or vertex two.
可能经过顶点一或者顶点二的最短路径
Why not? You could define it in this way.
为什么不呢？你完全可以这样定义它
It turns out,
然后得出
then when you increase k,
当你增大k时
you only have to think about one new vertex.
你只要考虑新的顶点就好了
Here, we had to take min over all k.
这里 我们必须算所有k的最小值
Now we know which k to look at.
现在我已经知道要看哪个k了
OK, maybe that made sense.
可能这就讲得通了
Maybe it's not quite obvious yet.
可能它现在依旧不是很明显
But I'm going to redo this claim, redo a recurrence.
但是我会重新做这个证明  重做这个循环
So, maybe first I should say some obvious things.
那么 我可能先要说明一些明显的事情
So, if I want delta of ij of the shortest pathway,
如果我想要这个最短路径中的δ(i,j)
well, just take all the vertices.
只需要用到所有的顶点
So, take c_ij superscript n.
用c_ij  上标n
That's everything. And this even works,
这就是全部了  这就可以能算出来了
this is true even if you have a negative weight cycle.
即使你有一个负权环也可以
Although, again, we're going to sort of ignore
虽然我们还是会忽略掉负权环
negative weight cycles as long as we can detect them.
只要我们能检测它们的话
And, another simple case is if you have, well,
另一个简单的情况是 如果你有 呃
c_ij to zero. Let me put that in the claim
c_ij 上标0的话  让我把这个写进证明里
to be a little bit more consistent here.
跟前面保持一致
So, here's the new claim.
那么这里是个新的证明
If we want to compute c_ij superscript zero, what is it?
如果我们想计算c_ij上标0，这是什么？
Superscript zero means I really shouldn't
上标0的意思是我不会用到
use any intermediate vertices.
任何的中间的媒介点
So, this has a very simple answer,
那么  这就有了一个非常简单的答案
a three letter answer.
答案只有三个字母
So, it's not zero.
所以不是0
It's four letters. What's that?
zero有四个字母  那是啥？
Nil. No, not working yet.
空？不是  不是这个
It has some subscripts, too.
它也包含一些下标字符
So, the definition would be,
这个定义就是
what's the shortest path weight from i to j
从i到j的最短路径是什么？
when you're not allowed to use any intermediate vertices?
当你被禁止使用任何中介点时
[student]Inaudible
[学生]:....
[Prof]:Sorry?
[教授]:没听清？
[Prof]:So, yeah, it has a very simple name.
[教授]:好吧 它有一个非常简单的名字
That's the tricky part. All right, so if i equals j,
这就是它的诡异之处  好了  那么如果i=j
you're clever, right,
好聪明喔  没错
open bracket i equals j means one, well, OK.
去掉括号  i=j的意思就是1   好吧
It sort of works, but it's not quite right.
这也行   但并不是非常准确
In fact, I want infinity if i does not equal j.
事实上 我要的是正无穷 如果i不等于j的话
And I want to zero if i equals j, a_ij, good.
如果i等于j  i就是零  a_ij   很好
I think it's a_ij. It should be, right?
我认为它是a_ij  它也应该是的 对吧？
Maybe I'm wrong.
可能我错了
Right, a_ij. So it's essentially not what I said.
是吧 就是a_ij  因为本质上 这不是我说的
That's the point.
这才是关键
If i does not equal j,
如果i不等于j
you still have to think about
你还需要考虑
a single edge connecting i to j, right?
一个连接i和j的单边 是吧？
OK, so that's a bit of a subtlety.
好吧 这是有点微妙
This is only intermediate vertices,
这只是中间的媒介点
so you could still go from i to j via a single edge.
因此你仍然可以经由一个单边连接i到j
That will cost a_ij.
那样花费就是a_ij
If there is an edge: infinity.
如果有一条边：无穷
If there isn't one: that is a_ij.
如果没有：那就是a_ij
So, OK, that gets us started.
好的 让我们开始吧
And then, we want a recurrence.
接着  我们需要做一个循环
And, the recurrence is, well,
这个循环就是 好吧
maybe you get away with all the vertices that you had before
可能你不需要用你之前用到的所有的顶点
so if you want to know paths that use one up to k,
因此 如果你想知道用到顶点1到k的路径
maybe I just use one up to k minus one.
可能只需要用到1到k-1就好
You could try that. Or, you could try using k.
你可以试一下   或者你可以试着用一下k
So, either you use k or you don't.
因此  你可以用或者不用K
If you don't, it's got to be this.
如果你不用  那就会是这样
If you do, then you've got to go to k.
如果你用  那么你必须经过k
So why not go to k at the end?
所以为什么不以k结束呢？
So, you go from i to k using the previous vertices.
你从i走到k之前用到的顶点
Obviously, you don't want to repeat k in there.
很显然 你不想再重复走一次k
And then, you go from k to j
那么你需要从k到j
somehow using vertices that are not k.
这时用到的顶点不是k
This should be pretty intuitive.
这些应该是非常直观的
Again, I can draw a picture.
我可以再画一个图
So, either you never go to k,
所以 要么你们从来没到过k
and that's this wiggly line.
就是这样一个弯弯的线
You go from i to j using things
你从i到j  用到的顶点
only one up to k minus one. In other words,
仅仅是1到k-1  换句话说
here we have to use one up to k.
这里说 我们不得不用1到k
So, this just means don't use k.
那么 这一条是不用k的路径
So, that's this thing.
所以 这是这个值
Or, you use k somewhere in the middle there.
或者  你在中间的某些地方用到k
OK, it's got to be one of the two.
好了  肯定是这两者二选一
And in this case,
而在这种情况下
you go from i to k using only smaller vertices,
从i到k 你仅需要用比k少的顶点
because you don't want to repeat k.
因为你并不用经过k
And here, you go from k to j
这里 你从k到j
using only smaller labeled vertices.
也仅用比k少的顶点
So, every path is one of the two.
每条路径都是这两者其中之一
So, we take the shortest of these two subproblems.
所以 在这两个子问题中 我们取最短那条
That's the answer.
这就是答案
So, now we have a min of two things.
现在 我们就得到两个东西的最小值了
It takes constant time to compute.
它需要常数的时间来计算
So, we get a cubic algorithm.
因此 我们得到一个三次算法
So, let me write it down.
让我先写下来
So, this is the Floyd-Warshall algorithm.
这就是Floyd-Warshall算法
I'll write the name again. You give it a matrix A.
我再写一遍这个名字  给它输入一个矩阵A
That's all it really needs to know.
这就是它所需要知道的全部数据
It codes everything. You copy C to A.
剩下的都是代码  你把A复制给C
That's the warm up. Right at time zero, C equals A.
这只是个热身 刚好时间为0时 C=A
And then you just have these three loops
接着你有三重循环
for every value of k, for every value of i,
对于每一个k值   每一个i值
and for every value of j. You compute that min.
每一个j值   你都算出这个最小值
And if you think about it a little bit,
如果你对仔细一想
that min is a relaxation.
这个最小值就是一个松弛法
Surprise, surprise.
喵了个咪的
So, that is the Floyd-Warshall algorithm.
这就是Floyd-Warshall算法
And, the running time is clearly n^3,
现在很清楚了 它的运行时间是n^3
three nested loops, constant time inside.
三个嵌套循环  最里层时间为常数
So, we're finally getting something
我们终于有成果了
that is never worse than Bellman-Ford.
它肯定不会比Bellman-Ford差
In the sparse case, it's the same.
在稀疏情况下 两者是相同
And anything denser,
在稍微密集的情况下
the number of edges is super linear.
这个边的数量是超线性的
This is strictly better than Bellman-Ford.
这肯定要比 Bellman-Ford好多了
And, it's better than everything we've seen so far
它也是我们见过的最好的
for all pair shortest paths.
全对最短路径问题的解法
And, this handles negative weights; very simple algorithm
它还能处理负权值的问题   非常简单的算法
even simpler than the one before.
甚至比前一个都简单
It's just relaxation within three loops.
它只是三个循环里的松弛操作而已
What more could you ask for? And we need to check that
还能比它更好吗？ 我们还需要检查一下
this is indeed what min we're computing here,
这是否真的是我们要算的最小值
except that the superscripts are omitted.
除了这些被省略的上标字符
That's, again, a bit of hand waving a bit.
那其实又是 可以忽略不写的
It's OK to omit subscripts
忽略上标是可以的
because that can only mean that
因为那就仅仅意味着
you're doing more relaxation that you should be.
你要更多应该做的松弛操作
Doing more relaxations can never hurt you.
做多一点松弛总是好的
In particular, we do all the ones that we have to.
尤其是 我们做的都是我们必须做的事情
Therefore, we find the shortest path weights.
因此  我们找到了着最短路径权值
And, again, here, we're assuming that
再有 这里 我们假设
there is no negative weight cycles.
没有负权环
It shouldn't be hard to find them,
要把它找出来也不难
but you have to think about that a little bit.
但是你不得不多考虑一下
OK, you could run another round of Bellman-Ford,
好了  你可以再跑一圈Bellman-Ford
see if it relaxes in a new edges again.
看它是否又松弛了新的一条边
For example,
比如说
I think there's no nifty trick for that version.
但我觉得这并没有什么酷炫的技巧
And, we're going to cover,
同时  我们接下来讲讲
that's our second algorithm for all pairs shortest paths.
那就是我们求解全对最短路径的第二个算法
Before we go up to the third algorithm,
在我们讲到第三个算法之前
which is going to be the cleverest of them all,
这也是它们之中最聪明的算法
the one Ring to rule them all, to switch trilogies,
唯我独尊 独领风骚
we're going to take a little bit of a diversion, side story
我们讲讲一点题外话  坊间杂谈
whatever, and talk about transitive closure briefly.
是啥都好 我们简要讲一下传递闭包
This is just a good thing to know about.
这是一个值得了解的东西
And, it relates to the algorithms we've seen so far.
它跟我们目前为止所了解的算法有关
So, here's a transitive closure problem.
那么 这有一个传递闭包问题
I give you a directed graph, and for all pair vertices,
我给你一个有向图  对于所有顶点对
i and j, I want to compute this number.
i和j   我想计算一个数值
It's one if there's a path from i to j.
如果从i到j存在一条路径  则为1
From i to j, and then zero otherwise.
从i到j   否则返回0
OK, this is sort of like a boring adjacency matrix
这就像是一个无聊的邻接矩阵一样
with no weights, except it's about paths
但没有加上权数  不过它是跟路径有关
instead of being about edges.
而不是跟边有关
OK, so how can I compute this?
那么  我要怎么计算这个？
That's very simple.
这非常简单
How should I compute this?
我应该怎么算？
This gives me a graph in some sense.
这个问题会给我一个输入图
This is adjacency matrix of a new graph
这是一个新图的邻接矩阵
called the transitive closure of my input graph.
称为我这个输入图的传递闭包
So？
然后呢？
[student]:Inaudible
[学生]:...
[Prof]:breadth first search, yeah, good.
[教授]:广度优先搜索  是的  非常好
So, all I need to do is find shortest paths,
那么  我所需要做的就是找到最短路径
and if the weights come out infinity,
而且如果这些权值是无穷大
then there's no path. If it's less than infinity,
那也就是没有路径了  如果它小于无穷大
that there's a path. And so here,
那就存在一条路径  所以这里
so you are saying maybe I don't care about the weights,
你说可能我不在乎这些权值
so I can run breadth first search n times,
我可以运行广度优先搜索n次
and that will work indeed. So, if we do B times BFS,
那确实是有用的  因此  如果我们用B次BFS
so it's maybe weird that I'm covering here in the middle,
可能我中途插讲这个有点奇怪
but it's just an interlude. So, we have,
就当是小插曲把  那么  我们有
then, something like V times E.
BFS的复杂度大概是O(V*E)
OK, you can run any of these algorithms.
好的 你可以尝试这里的任何一个算法
You could take Floyd-Warshall for example.
你可以用Floyd-Warshall算法做试验
Why not?
为什么不呢
OK, then it would just be V^3 I mean,
它的复杂度会是O(V^3)
you could run in any of these algorithms
你可以在任一这些算法中进行运算
with weights of one or zero,
用1或者0做为权值
and just check whether the values are infinity or not.
只要检验一下这些数值是否是无穷大
So, I mean, t_ij equals zero, if and only if
好了  我的意思是  t_ij=0 当且仅当
the shortest path weight from i to j is infinity.
从i到j的的最短路径权值为无穷时
So, just solve this.
这样就解决了
This is an easier problem than shortest paths.
这是一个比最短路径要简单的问题
It is, in fact, strictly easier in a certain sense,
它实际上  真的很简单
because what's going on with transitive closure,
因为这只是传递闭包而已
and I just want to mention this out of interest
我也只是出于兴趣才谈及它的
because transitive closure is a useful thing to know about.
因为传递闭包是一个有用的东西
Essentially, what we are doing,
本质上来讲 我们正在做的
let me get this right,
看看有没有说错
is using a different set of operators.
使用的是另一套的运算规则
We're using or and and,
我们正在使用“或”和“与”
a logical or and and instead of min and plus,
用逻辑上的“或”和“与”  来替换最小值和加法
OK, because we want to know,
因为我们想知道
if you think about a relaxation, in some sense,
如果你考虑松弛法 某种程度上
maybe I should think about it in terms of this min.
可能我要根据这个最小值来考虑
So, if I want to know, is there a pathway from i to j
如果我想知道  是否存在一条从i到j的路径
that uses vertices labeled one through k in the middle?
它中间用到了标有1到k的顶点？
Well, either there is a path
要么有一条路径
that doesn't use the vertex k,
它没有用到顶点k
or there is a path that uses k,
要么那条路径用到了k
and then it would have to look like that.
那它就会像是那样
OK, so there would have to be a path here,
肯定有这样的一条路
and there would have to be a path there.
也肯定有那样的一条路
So, the min and plus get replaced with or and and.
用“或”和“与”来替换求最小值和加法
And if you remember, this used to be plus,
如果你还记得  这里曾经是加号
and this used to be product in the matrix world.
这里原来在矩阵中是乘积
So, plus is now like or. And, multiply is now like and,
加号现在就是“或”   乘号则是“与”了
which sounds very good, right?
这听起来非常带感 是吧？
Plus does feel like or, and multiply does feel like and
加法的确像是“或”  而乘法的确也像是“与”
if you live in a zero-one world. So, in fact,
如果你是生活在二进制的世界里的话   事实上
this is not quite the field Z mod two,
这并不是神马Zmod2域
but this is a good, nice, field to work in.
但这是个很好很很强大的代数域
This is the Boolean world.
这是只有布尔函数知道的世界
So, I'll just write Boole.
我就写布尔好了
Good old Boole knows all about this.
布尔大神对这些东西很熟悉
It's like his master's thesis, I think.
这貌似是他的硕士论文
Talking about Boolean algebra.
谈一下这个布尔代数
And, this actually means that
这事实上意味着
you can use fast matrix multiply.
你可以使用快速矩阵乘法
You can use Strassen's algorithm,
你可以使用Strassen's算法
and the fancier algorithms, and you can compute
或其他更牛的算法  同时你也可以
the transitive closure in sub-cubic time.
在次立方的时间里 计算传递闭包
So, this is sub cubic if the edges are sparse.
如果这些边是稀疏的  这就是次立方
But, it's cubic in the worst case
但最坏情况下就是立方了
if there are lots of edges. This is cubic.
如果有很多边的话  这就是立方
You can actually do better using Strassen.
事实上你用Strassen可以做得更好
So, I'll just say you can do it.
因此  我也只是说你可以这样做
No details here. I think it should be,
这应该没什么好细讲的
so in fact, there is a theorem.
事实上 这里有个定理
This is probably not in the textbook,
它可能不在课本上
but there's a theorem that says
但是确实这么个定理说
transitive closure is just as hard as matrix multiply.
传递闭包就跟矩阵乘法一样难求
OK, they are equivalent.
它们是等价的
Their running times are the same.
它们的运算时间也是相同的
We don't know how long it takes
我们不知道它需要多久
to do a matrix multiply over a field.
在一个域上进行一个矩阵乘法运算
It's somewhere between n^2 and n^2.3.
它应该在n^2到n^2.3之间
But, whatever the answer is
但是 不管答案是什么
same for transitive closure.
它跟传递闭包是一样的
OK, there's the interlude.
这就是我们的小插曲
And that's where we actually
事实上 这就是我们
get to use Strassen and friends.
开始用Strassen和其他好帮手的地方
Remember, Strassen was n to the log base two of seven algorithm.
记得吗？Strassen是n的以二为底log 7次方的算法
Remember that, especially on the final.
记牢哟  尤其在期末考的时候
Those are things you should have at the tip of your tongue
那些东西是你应该张口就来的
OK, the last algorithm we're going to cover
好的 这是我们要讲的最后一个算法
is really going to build on
它真的是建立在...
what we saw last time Johnson's algorithm.
我们上次了解的Johnson算法之上
And, I've lost some of the running times here.
我在这里已经失去了一些运算时间了
But, when we had unweighted graphs,
但是  当我们有未加权的图时
we could do all pairs really fast,
我们可以很快地进行全对运算
just as fast as a single source Bellman-Ford.
就想单源Bellman-Ford算法一样快
That's kind of nifty.
非常漂亮
We don't know how to improve
我们不知道要怎么提高...
Bellman-Ford in the single source case.
在单源条件下的Bellman-Ford算法
So, we can't really help
因此 我们真的没办法
to get anything better than V times E.
得到任何比V*E更好的东西
And, if you remember running V times Dijkstra,
如果你记得运算V次Dijkstra
V times Dijkstra was about the same.
V次Dijkstra差不多也是这样的
So, just put this in the recall bubble here:
我把它写进这个“复习泡泡”里
V times Dijkstra would give us V times E plus V^2 log V.
V次Dijkstra的复杂度是O( V*E+V^2 log(V) )
And, if you ignore that log factor, this is just VE.
如果你忽略log因子  就只是VE
OK, so this was really good. Dijkstra was great.
好 非常好 Dijkstra算法很好很强大
And this was for nonnegative edge weights.
这适用于非负权边
So, with negative edge weights,
那么  在负权边的情况下
somehow we'd like to get the same running time.
或许 我们也想得到相同的运算时间
Now, how might I get the same running time?
那现在 我们要怎么得到相同的运算时间？
Well, it would be really nice if I could use Dijkstra.
如果我可以使用Dijkstra  那就真的太好了
Of course, Dijkstra doesn't work with negative weights.
当然  Dijkstra算法对负权值不起作用
So what could I do? What would I hope to do?
那么我该怎么做呢？我希望怎么做呢？
What could I hope to? Suppose I want,
我希望能怎样？假设我想
in the middle of the algorithm,
在算法中间
it says run Dijkstra n times.
它要运算Dijkstra n次
Then, what should I do to prepare for that?
那么  我要做些什么准备工作？
Make all the weights positive, or nonnegative.
令所有的权数都变为正的或者非负
Why not, right? We're being wishful thinking.
好吧  来一发  这是个有前途的思路
That's what we'll do.
这就是我们要做的
So, this is called graph re-weighting.
这就是所谓的图重加权
And, what's cool is we actually already know how to do it.
最赞的就是 事实上我们已经知道要怎么做了
We just don't know that we know how to do it.
我们只是不知道我们已经知道了而已
But I know that we know that we know how to do it.
但我知道我们其实知道我们要怎样做
You don't yet know that we know that
你还不知道其实我们知道
I know that we know how to do it.
我知道我们要怎么做
So, it turns out you can re-weight the vertices.
所以 实际上你们可以对顶点进行权重调整
So, at the end of the last class someone asked me,
上节课结束的时候有人问我
can you just, like, add the same weight to all the edges?
您能只是  比如说  给所有的边加上同样的权值吗？
That doesn't work.
那样没用的
Not quite, because different paths
没什么用  因为不同的路径
have different numbers of edges.
有不同的边数
What we are going to do
我们将要做的
is add a particular weight to each vertex.
是给每一个顶点都加上一个特别的权重
What does that mean?
那是什么意思呢？
Because we really only have weights on the edges,
因为我们只是边有权值
here's what we'll do.
而这是我们要做的
We'll re-weight each edge, so, (u,v),let's say,
我们要调整每条边界的权重  因此(u,v)  我们说
going to go back into graph speak instead of matrix speak,
回归到用图表示 而不是用矩阵表示
(u,v) instead of i and j,
用的是(u,v)而不是i和j
and we'll call this modified weight w_h.
我们将称之为修正权数w_h
h is our function.
h是我们的函数
It gives us a number for every vertex.
它给每一个顶点一个值
And, it's just going to be the old weight of that edge
而它将会给旧的边权值
plus the weight of the start vertex
加上起点的权值
minus the weight of the terminating vertex.
再减去终点的权值
I'm sure these have good names.
我确信这些都有很好的命名
One of these is the head, and the other is the tail,
其中一个是头 另一个是尾巴
but I can never remember which.
但是我从来记不住哪个是哪个
OK, so we've directed edge (u,v)
好了 我们有一条有向边(u,v)
Just add one of them; subtract the other.
只要加上它们中的一个 减去另一个
And, it's a directed edge,
因为它是条有向边
so that's a consistent definition.
所以 这是个一致性的定义
OK, so that's called re-weighting.
这就是所谓的权重调整
Now, this is actually a theorem.
这实际上是一个定理
If you do this, then, let's say,
如果你这样做  那么我们说
for any vertices, u and v in the graph,
对于任何顶点 这图中的u和v
for any two vertices,
对于任意两个点
all paths from u to v have the same weight
所有从u到v的路径的权值
as they did before, well, not quite.
就跟它们以前一样  好吧 不完全是
They have the same re-weighting.
它们调整后的权重是相同的
So, if you look at all the different paths and you say,
所以 如果你观察所有不同的路径 你会问
well, what's the difference between vh, well,
vh之间有什么不同吗？
sorry, let's say delta, which is the old shortest paths,
说错了 不好意思  我们说δ是之前的那种最短路径
and delta sub h, which is the shortest path weights
而δ_h 则是根据这种新的加权函数
according to this new weight function,
所求出来的最短路径权值
then that difference is the same.
(所有新路径和旧路径)之间的差值是一样的
So, we'll say that all these paths
所以 我们说所有的这些路径
are re-weighted by the same amounts.
都以此相同的总量重新调整了权值
OK, this is actually a statement about
这事实上 是一个
all paths, not just shortest paths.
关于所有路径 而不仅仅是最短路径的命题
There we go. OK, to how many people
就是这样 有多少人
is this obvious already?
已经听懂了的？
A few, yeah, it is.
有一些  好吧
And what's the one word?
哪个词可以一语道破？
OK, it's maybe not that obvious.
好吧 它可能不是很明显
All right, shout out the word when you figure it out.
没关系 当你们想到的时候就大声吼出来
Meanwhile, I'll write out this rather verbose proof.
而同时 我将把详细的证明过程写出来
There's a one word proof, still waiting.
其实用一个词就可以证明了  我还在等
So, let's just take one of these paths
好 我们选择其中一条路径
that starts at u and ends at v. Take any path.
以u开始 以v结束 任何一个路径都可以
We're just going to see what its
我们将看到
new weight is relative to its old weight.
它的新的权值与旧的权值是相对应的
And so, let's just write out w_h of the path,
我们写下这个路径的w_h
which we define in the usual way
用一般的定义方法
as the sum over all edges of the new weight
它是从v_i到v_(i+1)的
of the edge from v_i to v_i plus one.
所有的边的新加权之和
Do you have the word?
你们想到那个单词了吗
No? Tough puzzle then,
还没有？这看来略难啊
OK. So that's the definition of the weight of a path.
好了 这就是一条路径的权值的定义
And, then we know this thing
同时 我们知道的这个东西
is just w of v_i, v_i plus one.
就是w(v_i, v_(i+1))
I'll get it right, plus the weight of the first vertex,
把它写完  再加上第一个顶点的权值
plus, sorry, the re-weighting of v_i
再加上  对不起  是v_i的调整权值
minus the re-weighting of v_i plus one.
减去v_(i+1)的调整权值
This is all in parentheses that's summed over i.
这些都在一个大括号里 都是对i求和的
Now I need the magic word. Telescopes, good.
现在我要一个魔力单词  缩进法  相当好
Now this is obvious:
现在就很明显了
each of these telescopes with the next and previous,
每一个项都能前后缩进
except the very beginning and the very end.
除了最初和最终的两个之外
So, this is the sum of these weights of edges,
因此 这是所有边的权值之和
but then outside the sum,
但是在总和之外
we have plus h of v_1, and minus h of v_k.
我们再加上h(v_1)  减去h(v_k)
OK, those guys don't quite cancel.
好吧 这两项不会相互抵消
We're not looking at a cycle, just a path.
我们寻找的是一条路径 而非循环
And, this thing is just w of the path,
这就是路径w
as this is the normal weight of the path.
同时 这是路径的普通权值
And so the change,
那么不同点是
the difference between w_h of P and w of P is this thing,
w_h(p)和w(p)的差别就是这个东西
which is just h of u minus h of v. And, the point is
就是h(u)减去h(v)   重点是
that's the same as long as you fix the endpoints,
这一项到处都一样  只要你固定了端点
u and v, of the shortest path,
在最短路径中的u和v
you're changing this path weight
这样 你就调整了这条路径权值
by the same thing for all paths.
所有路径调整的幅度都一样
This is for any path from u to v,
这是对于任意从u到v的路径而言
and that proves the theorem.
那样就证明了这个定理
So, the one word here was telescopes.
所以这里的魔法单词就是 缩进法
These change in weights telescope over any path.
这些权值的变动在所有路径上都能缩进
Therefore, if we want to find shortest paths,
因此 如果我们想找到最短路径
you just find the shortest paths
你只要在这个重新调整的版本里
in this re-weighted version,
寻找最短路径就好
and then you just change it by this one amount.
然后再用这一个定量调整一下它
You subtract off this amount instead of adding it.
你只要减去这个数量 而不是加上这个数量
That will give you the shortest path weight
那你就会得到
in the original weights.
原来的最短路径加权
OK, so this is a tool.
好的 这是一个工具
We now know how to change weights in the graph.
现在我们已经明白如何调整图的权值
But what we really want is to change weights in the graph
但是 我们真正需要的是去调整图中的权值
so that the weights all come out nonnegative.
使得权值变为非负值
OK, how do we do that?
那么要怎么做呢？
Why in the world would there be a function, h,
这世界上怎么就有这种函数h
that makes all the edge weights nonnegative?
使得所有边的权值为非负呢？
It doesn't make sense. It turns out we already know.
这有点不科学  但看来我们都知道
So, I should write down this consequence.
我写一下这个推论
Let me get this in the right order. So in particular,
按照正确顺序写清楚 那么特别地
the shortest path changes by this amount.
最小的路径权值有了这一定量的变化
And if you want to know this value,
如果你算出这个值
you just move the stuff to the other side.
你就把这块移项到等式另一边
So, we compute deltas of h, then we can compute delta.
所以呢 我们计算出δ_h 然后再算出增量δ
That's the consequence here.
这就是我们的推论
How many people here pronounce this word corollary?
有多少人把这个单词发音成“磕了蚁”？
OK, and how many people pronounce it corollary?
那又有多少人把它发音成"磕错了蚁"？
Yeah, we are alone.
好吧  注定孤独一生
Usually get at least one other student,
通常应该还有一个学生才对
and they're usually Canadian or British or something.
而且呢 他们一般都是加拿大佬或英国佬神马的
I think that the accent.
我认为这就是口音
So, I always avoid pronouncing this word
所以我总是避免说这个词
unless I really think, it's corollary, and get it right.
除非我确信这是“磕了蚁”  而且可以发对了音
I at least say Z not Zed. OK, here we go.
至少我说的是Zii而不是Zed  好的 我们继续
So, what we want to do is find one of these functions.
所以我们要做的 就是找到一个这样的函数
I mean, let's just write down what we could hope to have.
我的意思是 我们来写一下什么想要得到的
We want to find a re-weighted function, h,
我们想要找到一个调整权值函数h
that assign weight to each vertex
给每一个顶点赋一个权值
such that w sub h u, v is nonnegative.
使得w_h(u,v) 是非负的
That would be great for all edges, all (u,v) in E.
对于所有集合E之中边(u,v)来说 这实在是太棒了
OK, then we could run Dijkstra.
好的 那我们就可以跑Dijkstra算法了
We could run Dijkstra, get the delta h's,
我们运行Dijkstra算法  算出δ_h的值
and then just undo the re-weighting,
然后撤销调整权值
and get what we want. And, that is Johnson's algorithm.
得出我们想要的值  这就是Johnson算法
The claim is that this is always possible.
这引理说  这始终是可行的
OK, why should it always be possible?
为什么始终是可行的呢？
Well, let's look at this constraint.
让我们看一下这个约束条件
w_h(u,v) is that.
w_h(u,v)等于
So, it's w(u,v) plus h(u) u minus h(v)
等于w(u,v) + h(u) - h(v)
should be nonnegative.
应该是非负的
Let me rewrite this a little bit.
让我再把它重写一下
I'm going to put these guys over here.
我要把这些项移到这边
That would be the right thing,
这是没问题的
h of v minus h of u is less than or equal to w of u,v.
h(v) - h(u) 小于或等于 w(u,v)
Does that look familiar? Did I get it right?
是不是看着很眼熟  我算对没有？
It should be right. Anyone seen that inequality before?
这应该是对的  有人曾经见过这条不等式吗？
[student]Inaudible
[学生]:...
[Prof]:Yeah, yes, correct answer.
[教授]:耶  是的  回答正确
OK, where?
在哪见过？
[student]Inaudible
[学生]:...
[Prof]:In a previous lecture?
[教授]:在上一节课上？
In the re-previous lecture.
我在上上次课上提到过
What is this called if I replace h with x?
这个叫什么？ 如果我用x替换h的话
Charles knows.
查哥知道
Good, anyone else remember
真是愉悦  还有谁记得？
all the way back to episode two?
好好回想下我在第二集说的话吧
I know there was a weekend.
我记得那是个浪漫的周末
What's this operator called?
这个运算叫什么？
Not subtraction but, I think I heard it,
不是减法  它是...  我好像听到答案了
oh man. All right, I'll tell you.
弱爆了 孩纸们  好吧  我告诉你们
It's a difference constraint, all right?
这是差分约束 好吧
This is the difference operator.
这是另一个差分运算
OK, it's our good friend difference constraints.
好的  这是我们的好朋友差分约束
So, this is what we want to satisfy.
那么 这是我们要满足的条件
We have a system of difference constraints.
我们有一套差分约束系统
h of V minus h of u should be, we want to find these.
h(v) 减去 h(u) 应该是  我们要求出这些东西
These are our unknowns. Subject to these constraints,
这些是未知数  被这些所约束
we are given the w's.  Now,
而我们已经给出了w  现在
we know when these difference constraints are satisfiable.
我们知道什么时候这些差分约束是可满足的
Can someone tell me
有人可以告诉我吗
when these constraints are satisfiable?
什么时候可以满足约束条件？
We know exactly when for any set of difference constraints.
我们当然知道 什么时候能满足任意的约束约束条件
You've got to remember the math.
数学也是背多分的  孩纸们
Terminology, I can understand.
如果是术语的话 我能理解
It's hard to remember words
背单词是很麻烦的
unless you're a linguist, perhaps.
除非你是语言学家
So, when is the system of
所以  什么时候这个
different constraints satisfiable?
差分约束系统是可以满足的？
All right, you should definitely … very good.
对  你们一定要... 非常好
[student]Inaudible
[学生]:...
[Prof]Yes, very good. Someone brought their lecture notes
[教授]:对  很好  有人带来了他的课堂笔记。
when the constraint graph has no negative weight cycles.
当约束图没有负权环时
Good, thank you.
很好 谢谢
Now, what is the constraint graph?
那么  什么是约束图？
OK, this has a one letter answer more or less.
好吧  这次的答案只有一个字母
I'll accept the one letter answer.
我接受这个一个字母的回答
What? A?
什么？A?
close. G.
接近了 是G  木哈哈
Yeah, I mean, same thing.
耶  其实都一样嘛
Yeah, so the constraint graph is essentially G.
所以所有的约束图基本上是G
Actually, it is G. The constraint graph is G, good.
事实上  就是G  约束图是G图  很好
And, we prove this by adding a new source vertex,
我们论证方法是 增加一个新的源点
and connecting that to everyone.
然后把它和其他点联系起来
But that's sort of beside the point.
不过那就和这个点无关了
That was in order to actually satisfy them.
其实这个点正是为了满足约束而存在的
But this is our characterization. So, if we assume that
但这是我们的特征 那如果我假设
there are no negative weight cycles in our graph,
在我们的图中没有负权环
which we've been doing all the time,
我们一直都这么做
then we know that this thing is satisfiable.
然后 我们就知道这个是可以满足的
Therefore, there is an assignment of this h's.
因此 这里有一个赋值函数h
There is a re-weighting that
所以 就有了一个调整权值函数
makes all the weights nonnegative.
使得所有的权值非负
Then we can run Dijkstra. OK, we're done.
然后我们就能运行Dijkstra算法了  大功告成
Isn't that cool? And how do we satisfy these constraints?
很神奇有木有！  那我们要如何满足这些约束呢？
We know how to do that with one run of Bellman-Ford,
我们知道怎么用一次Bellman-Ford来做
which costs order VE,
这会花费VE阶
which is less than V times Dijkstra.
小于V次Dijkstra算法
So, that's it, write down the details somewhere.
那么  就是这样  我找个位置写下这些
So, this is Johnson's algorithm.
那么 这就是Johnson算法
This is the fanciest of them all.
这是他们之中最高级的。
It will be our fastest,
也是最快捷的
all pairs shortest path algorithm.
全对最短路径算法
So, the claim is, we can find a function, h, from V to R
所以呢  结论就是  我们可以找到一个函数h 把V映射到R
Such that the modified weight of every edge
并满足对每条边的权数调整
is nonnegative for every edge (u,v) in our graph.
使得图中每条边(u,v)都为非负的
And, we do that using Bellman-Ford
而且 我们运用Bellman-Ford算法
to solve the difference constraints.
来解决差分约束
These are exactly the difference constraints that
正是这一些差分约束
we were born to solve that we learned to solve last time.
我们上节课学的知识 就是为了解决它而存在的
The graphs here are corresponding exactly
这里的这些图都是完全对应的
if you look back at the definition.
如果你仔细回顾定义的话
Or, Bellman-Ford will tell us that
或者  Bellman-Ford算法会告诉我们
there is a negative weight cycle.
图中存在一个负权环
OK, great, so it's not that we really have to assume that
爽吧 那么我们就不用真的去假设
there is no negative weight cycle. We'll get to know.
图里面没有负权环  我们待会就明白了
And if your fancy, you can actually
如果你很牛  你真的可以
figure out the minus infinities from this.
直接用它找出负无穷出来
But, at this point,
但是  现在
I just want to think about the case
我只考虑一种情况
where there is no negative weight cycle.
就是没有负权环
But if there is, we can find out that it exists,
但是如果有  我们可以找到它的存在
and that just tell the user. OK, then we'd stop.
然后告知用户  然后停止运算
Otherwise, there is no negative weight cycle.
否则的话  如果没有负权环
Therefore, there is an assignment
因此 会有一个赋值运算
that gives us nonnegative edge weights.
使得边权都变为非负的
So, we just use it. We use it to run Dijkstra.
那我们就用上它吧  拿它来运行Dijkstra算法
So, step two is, oh,
接下来 第二步就是  噢
I should say the running time of all this is V times E.
我得说一下所有这些的运行时间是V*E
So, we're just running Bellman-Ford
所以 我们就再输入图上
on exactly the input graph.
运行下Bellman-Ford算法
Plus, we add a source, if you recall,
另外 我们还添加了一个源  还记得吧
to solve a set of difference constraints.
来解决一整套差分约束
You add a source vertex, S,
你添加一个源顶点S
connected to everyone at weight zero,
跟其他所有点连接 权值为0
run Bellman-Ford from there
从那运行Bellman-Ford算法
because we don't have a source here.
因为这里没有源
We just have a graph.
我们只有一个图
We want to know all pairs.
我们想知道是全顶点对
So, this, you can use to find
所以这下  你可以通过它去找
whether there is a negative weight cycle anywhere.
是不是某个地方存在负权环
Or, we get this magic assignment.
或者 我们有这个神奇的赋值
So now, w_h is nonnegative,
所以现在  w_h是非负的
so we can run Dijkstra on w_h.
因此 我们能在w_h上跑Dijkstra算法
using w_h, so you compute w_h.
这里写用w_h  所以你就能算出w_h
That takes linear time.
这花费线性的时间
And, we run Dijkstra for each possible source.
然后我们为每个可能的源 都运行Dijkstra算法。
I'll write this out explicitly.
我会特别写明这一点的
We've had this in our minds several times.
我们脑子里想了千百遍了。
But, when we said n times Dijkstra
但是 当我们说n次Dijkstra算法
n times BFS, here it is.
n次BFS  这里就是
We want to compute delta sub h now, of u,v for all v
现在我们要计算所有v的δ_h(u,v)
and we do this separately for all u.
然后分开再算一遍所有u的
And so, the running time here is VE plus V^2 log V.
那这里的运行时间  就是O(VE+V^2 * log V)
This is just V times the running time of Dijkstra,
这个只是V次Dijkstra的运行时间
which is E plus V log V.
也就是 E + V log(V)
OK, it happens that this term is the same as this one,
我们发现这一项跟这个是一样的
which is nice, because that means step one
灰常不错  因为这意味着这第一步
costs us nothing asymptotically. OK, and then,
没有给我们增加复杂度  好了 然后
last step is, well, now we know delta h.
最后一步是  那么  现在我们知道了δ_h
We just need to compute delta.
我们就只要计算δ了
So, for each pair of vertices,
那么  对于每个点对
we'll call it (u,v), we just compute
用(u,v)表示  我们只计算
what the original weights would be,
它本来的权值是多少
so what delta (u,v) is.
也就是δ(u,v)是多少
And we can do that using this corollary.
我们可以用这个推论来做
It's just delta sub h, (u,v), minus h of u plus h of v.
所以这个就是 δ_h(u,v)-h(u)+h(v)
I got the signs right. Yeah, so this takes V^2 time,
好的我没写错  这个需要 V^2的时间
also dwarfed by the running time of Dijkstra.
跟Dijkstra算法的时间相比也是相形见拙
So, the overall running time of Johnson's algorithm
所以Johnson算法的整体运行时间
is just the running time of step two,
就是第二步的运行时间
running Dijkstra n times --
运行n次Dijkstra的时间
- which is pretty cool.
酷到无法直视啊
When it comes to single source shortest paths,
如果是单源最短路径的话
Bellman-Ford is the best thing for general weights.
对于一般权值来说 Bellman-Ford是最好的
Dijkstra is the best thing for nonnegative weights.
而对非负加权来说 Dijkstra是最好的
But for all pair shortest paths,
但是对于所有全对最短路径来说
we can skirt the whole negative weight issue
我们可以绕开整个负权值问题
by using this magic result from Bellman-Ford.
通过从Bellman-Ford得出的神奇的结果
But now, running Dijkstra n times, which is
运行n次的Dijkstra算法
still the best thing we know how to do,
已经是我们所知道的最好算法了
pretty much for the all pairs nonnegative weights,
对于所有非负权点对来说
now we can do it for general weights too,
但现在 对于一般权值来说也是最好了
which is a pretty nice combination
在我们讲过的技巧的组合里
of all the techniques we've seen.
这也是一个相当不错的组合了
In the trilogy, and along the way,
这三部曲  一路走来
we saw lots of dynamic programming,
我们看到大量的动态规划
which is always good practice.
这总是很好的方案
Any questions?
有问题吗？
This is the last new content lecture before the quiz.
这是测验前最后一次讲新的内容
On Wednesday it will be quiz review,
星期三将进行测验复习
if I recall correctly.
如果我没有记错的话
And then it's Thanksgiving, so there's no recitation.
然后就是感恩节了  就没有复习课了
And then the quiz starts on Monday.
然后  周一就开始测试了
So, study up. See you then.
好好学习吧孩纸们！ 愿算法与你同在！